<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Oleksandr Paraska</title>
    <link>https://shoniko.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Oleksandr Paraska</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://shoniko.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>About me</title>
      <link>https://shoniko.com/about-me/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://shoniko.com/about-me/</guid>
      <description>Hi! My name is Oleksandr Paraska. Currently I work at eyeo, exploring different ways you can apply progress in machine learning to ad blocking. My wife, my son and I currently live in Bonn, Germany.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Optimize for happiness</title>
      <link>https://shoniko.com/posts/optimize-for-happiness/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Apr 2007 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://shoniko.com/posts/optimize-for-happiness/</guid>
      <description>Optimize for happiness  Note: this is a copy of an original post from my Blogspot. It is a very old post, and does not necessary reflect my position now. I just keep it here for future references.
 Recently I came across the idea of happiness optimization. It basicly says something like - do what you like to do - that way the product will be better, and you wil be happier.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://shoniko.com/drafts/systematization/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://shoniko.com/drafts/systematization/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Intelligent content filtering</title>
      <link>https://shoniko.com/posts/post/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://shoniko.com/posts/post/</guid>
      <description>How do you know what a cat is?
It is certainly something furry, four-legged with a head and tail. But so is a dog. And a mouse. It certainly is something that meows - but some cats do not meow, yet we still agree they are cats. We can even (hopefully) agree that in the picture above there are three cats, even though we see nine legs, do not hear any meows, and see completely different color patterns on each.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>